A Guide to the Farrier Family Papers, 1894-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Farrier Family Papers, 1894-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1974-011
77.0 cu. ft. 55 boxes
Farrier family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Farrier Family Papers were donated to Newman Library in 1974.
Biographical/Historical Note
Martin P. (1869-1946) and his son, Andrew L. (?-1972) Farrier, lawyers in Pearisburg, Giles County, Virginia. Each was a trial lawyer and each served in the Virginia General Assembly. As a law firm they individually and collectively represented some of the most important industries in Southwest Virginia, including the Norfolk and Western Railway Company, Appalachian Power Company, and several coal and lumber interests.
Scope and Content
The collection includes files from the firm of Williams and Farrier, later Farrier and Farrier. Materials include copies of deeds, title searches, land transactions, estate matters, loan contracts, divorce suits, small claims collection suits, ledgers, and correspondence. Additional details of some files are included in the original inventories, available on request.
Arrangement
The collection is in its original order from the time of its donation. Boxes 1-37, 43 and 44 contain files from the law firms of Williams and Farrier, Farrier and Farrier, and Williams and Farrier and Farrier (the name changed successively over time), as well as some personal papers from the Farrier family. Boxes 38-42 and 45-52 contain ledgers, loose files, and correspondence. Boxes 53 and 54 contain correspondence, arranged alphabetically within six individual letter boxes. Box 55 contains maps.
Index Terms
Persons:
Farrier, Andrew L., d. 1972; Farrier, Martin P., 1869-1946
Geographical Names:
Bland County (Va.); Floyd County (Va.); Giles County (Va.)
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Railroad
Contents List
- Box 1, 1904-1951 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content
  Two series of files from a wooden cabinet. The first set deals mainly with land and estate matters, mostly from the early 1940s. The second set concerns estates. Files are from the office of Pearisburg attorneys, M. P. and A. L. Farrier.
  - Various Land Matters
    Typed and hand written material concerning land transactions between Welford W. Dowdy and Virginia Dowdy Broadwell, Clarence Sarver, et al, and Everett Scott, Riley Warden and A. B. Allen, Henry Dalton and J.F. Rushbrook, Hallie Porterfield Stower and F. R. Parr and a title to the Mountain View Subdivision in Pearisburg, Va. March 1946-June 1948.
  - Jeff Carson Estate, April 1944-November 1945.
  - J. Kent Eaton Estate, July 1944-September 1945
  - Federal Forest Service
    Farrier and Farrier negotiate several land transactions between Files County land owners and the USDA Forest Service. Owners are trying to capitalize on the high demand for lumber resulting from its new usage in World War II. December 1935-July 1943.
  - Little Stony Game and Fish Preserve
    Slight material concerning debts and taxes of the Little Stony Game and Fish Preserve, and a statement declaring M. P. Farrier trustee of the Preserve. See Federal Forest Service file concerning sale of the Preserve. February 1940-October 1944.
  - Wirt B. Snidow (2 files), November 1918-February 1947; October 1940-June 1947.
  - Virginian Railway Co. vs. Town of Narrows (2 files), March-November 1944; January 1944-November 1945.
  - Wills
    Various wills, presumably written by A. L. Farrier, for the following people: John H. Givens; Erastus E. Cook; Walter Gauties; James M. Dillard; Ada S. Lambert; Vance S. Lambert; William T. Doyle; Grace J. Kirk; G. A. Kessinger; and John Hundley Eller. April 1946-December 1951.
  - Income Tax Returns--A. L. Farrier, 1942-1947.
  - Associates Coal and Gas Co.
    An association of Southwest Virginia businessmen, including M. P. Farrier, F. E. and W. B. Snidow, Martin Williams, and other prominent Giles County men, established for the purpose of exploiting coal and gas deposits in the area. The company does not appear to have done well. File contains mostly handwritten statements concerning debts and assets. June 1925-September 1934.
  - Bancroft-Whitney Company
    Substantial correspondence with Bancroft-Whitney Co. concerning the purchases of law books by M. P. and A. L. Farrier. March 1927-October 1946.
  - Boyles, J. S. Estate, February 1920-February 1923.
  - Bland County Lumber Co. v. Mrs. A. A. Strange, 1921-1937.
  - Bland Lumber Company Maps, July 1911-September 1915.
  - Bland County Lumber--Various
    When the Bland County Lumber Co. went bankrupt some time after 1936, a commissioner was appointed to investigate the company's liabilities and assets. Material in this file consists mainly of M. P. Farrier's handwritten answers to a series of questions put to him by the commissioner. Farrier gives detailed information concerning land holdings and company debts. See related Bland Lumber Co. files (Bland County Lumber Co. v. Mrs. A. A. Strange and Bland Lumber Company Maps).
  - Butt Estate, August 1922-August 1929.
  - Charlton, V. E. Estate, November 1913-November 1922.
  - Cole, J. J.--Contracts, Calculations, February 1912-August 1920.
  - Commissioner of Accounts, Giles County (2 files)
    In his capacity as County Commissioner of Accounts, M. P. Farrier reviewed the accounts submitted by the administrator for the following estates: M. E. Gooch; A. J. Straley; O. S. Dillow; J. A. Stafford; W. E. P. Lucus; W. B. Staffoed; A. J. Smith; I. W. Peters; W. L. Price; J. A. Gusler; C. W. Shannon; L. A. Ritter; C. W. Straley; J. A. Bane; G. M. Henderson; and C. W. Meredith. He likewise reviewed the accounts submitted by guardians for the following people: A. J. Smith; W. O. Smith; M. L. Collins; M. W. Runions. January 1928-January 1938.
    Similar to the above for following estates: J. W. T. Henderson; J. D. French; J. W. Stafford; E. G. Sarver; M. S. Woodyard; J. R. Emmons; M. T. Barger; W. A. Johnson; E. S. Johnson; J. F. Jewel; and John Brill. Also for guardians of M. L. Collins; Dewey and Almoa Daves; Margaret McNeely; George Akers, and Lewis Rowe. May 1934-November 1939.
  - Davis, Minnie F.--Guardian
    M. P. Farrier, as Commissioner of Accounts for Giles County, reviews the statements of Minnie F. Davis, guardian for Leonard A. French, a minor. April-July 1932.
  - Commissioner of Accounts (5 folders)
    Similar to above files for following estates: G. G. Lindsey; S. K. Bane; J. E. Tripton; M. G. J. Snidow; G. T. Fuller; P. N. Southern; J. H. Spangler; J. R. Johnston; A. E. Dunford; M. W. Mallory; Edward Lowe; Fount Johnson; J. T. S. Hoge; R. L. Elmore; J. W. Turner; J. M. Ratcliff; J. M. Farley; J. M. Givens. Likewise for the guardians of Donald and Arthur Stafford; M. L. Collins; Frank and Mary L. Johnston; L. B. and M. W. Bowen; O. B. Snidow; A. E. Epling; trusteeship over Harry J. James. April 1936-October 1940.
    Similar to the above for the following estates: L. S. McElroth; E. B. French; M.E. Mottesheard; D. F. Hale; S. C. Overstreet; F. W. Williams; P. J. Muncy; S. D. Lucas; L. J. Smith; Albert Hutchinson; Sylvester Snodgrass; H. W. Morris; S. T. Pack; C. L. Simpkins; G. H. Dennis; W. B. Knight; I. P. Thompson; G. A. Shumate; Tom Smith; W. S. Dean; J. W. Turner; Frances Williams; N. E. Buckland; A. J. Straley; F. L. Johnston; J. L. Straley; and B. S. Huffman. Also for guardians of Robert Croy; Ernest Robertson; Fay, Louise, Irene and Johnston Smith; Brackett Porterfield; Rhoda E. Eplling; Llwellyn and Mary T. Johnson; Lula Porterfield; M. E. Stafford; Ilean and Crackett Straley; L. A. French; and Larry Woodyard. Wills of J. A. Adair and W. F. Webb. December 1922-April 1933.
    Similar to above for the following estates: W. D. Ratcliff; E. S. Ratcliff; J. W. Meredith; L. M. Whittaker; A. J. Straley; J. E. Carson; F. H. Stafford; J. S. Eaton; E. J. Morris; H. H. Smith; S. K. Woods; Joshua Radford; A. W. Snidow; G. G. Lindsey; P. B. Wimmer and O. L. Williams. Also for guardians of Goodlow Straley, Johnson Smith, and I. S. Vaught. April 1937-January 1939.
    Similar to above for the following estates: G. W. Nowlin; L. M. Thompson; J. D. Mann; A. B. hare; Sallie Hambrick; R. A. Pauley; S. V. White; A. D. Collins; A. P. Saunders; J. R. Emmons; Annie Dickinson; W. H. Thomas; J. M. Wright; C. B. Williams; G. L. Bane; W. T. Kirk; Louise Jarvis; S. L. Buckland; H. W. Mann; B. F. Riddle; M. F. Cooper; R. V. Wheeler; J. J. Topsail; G. G. Lindsey. Also for the guardians of Louis and O. P. Ferrell and Polly Ann and J. A. Eppley. September 1938-October 1943.
    Similar to the above for the following estates: E. L. Buchanan; E. E. Montgomery; J. T. Bishop; M. A. Muncy; J. H. Duncan; Gertude Fisher; W. H. Reynolds; C. H. Wimmer; C. E. Cooper; B. M. Johnston; H. H. Wolfe; O. B. Quick; L. C. Williams; and Nannie Gordon. All material in this file is handwritten indicating that the statements are not final drafts. Also, about half have uncashed check to F. E. Snidow attached, indicating they were not recorded by the county clerk. September 1942-May 1945.
  - Dunn Estates, June 1922-September 1924.
  - Deeds, Contracts, etc., July 1909-October 1921.
  - E. S. Dennis estate--Letters and Statements (2 files)
    M. P. Farrier acting for the interest of the E. S. Dennis heirs, disposes of the property and real estate of E. S. Dennis in an attempt to satisfy the debts of the deceased. Extensive correspondence between Farrier and the two heirs. September 1921-February 1925.
    Statements of claim against Dennis estate. March 1922-January 1930.
- Box 2, 1875-1947 (Box 2)
  Office files of M. P. Farrier (abbreviated MPF).
  - Eaton, H. L. Estate, August 1922-April 1924.
  - J. D. Foote
    Present are the receipts showing land taxes paid by J. D. Foote for 1916-1919. Majority of the material consists of deeds showing the extensive land holdings of Foote in Giles County. November 1875-January 1926.
  - MPF--Personal
    Present are two receipts for a burial blot near Pearisburg, a Christmas card and Valentine card from his wife, and two letters from an acquaintance in Richmond. February 1922-May 1930.
  - Giles County--Property Valuations, etc.
    MPF was a member of the county committee which investigated the prospect of establishing a county budget. The committee felt that a budget was unnecessary since the county's revenue was large enough to afford the freedom of action provided by a non-budget system. A detail statement of all assessed real estate and property in Giles County is presented, as well as a statement of yearly county expenditures. Files also contain a copy of the Pearisburg Virginian, dated April 1, 1920, which has a series of articles and editorials concerning a county board for road improvement. October 1918-March 1927.
  - General Assembly
    Some correspondence, but most material consists of copies of bills MPF wanted presented to the General Assembly. Bills concern: condemnation of private land; collection of taxes and levies; construction and maintenance of division fences; grants of public land; a new charter for the town of Narrows; terms of court for Giles County; sentencing felony convictions; right of land ownership; awarding and dissolving of injunctions; bonding of committees; certificates of acknowledgement; and regulation of judgments. June 1922-April 1928.
  - Groseclose Filling Station, March 1927-December 1928.
  - General Assembly
    MPF was the patron of several bills before the General Assembly on the following subjects: partnerships, sale of estate property and dissolution injunctions. Copies of numerous other bills are included, received by MPF as a member of the General Assembly. February 1932-December 1944.
  - Hoge, James, December 1915-August 1927.
  - Hardwick, A. J. Estate, March 1926-June 1928.
  - Lucas, L. L.--Administrator for the C. H. Lucas Estate, August 1923-July 1926.
  - Leffell, G. W. Estate, July 1926-June 1929.
  - Layman, G. W.
    Extensive correspondence between Layman and MPF concerning cases on which they worked together. Layman, attorney from New Castle, seems to have collaborated with Farrier throughout their extensive careers. October 1923-July 1945.
  - Meadows, J. W., Executor of J. E. Stafford, November 1923-December 1924.
  - Pulaski and Giles Mutual Insurance Company
    MPF aided in the revision of the Pulaski and Giles Mutual Insurance Co. by-laws. He was also a policy holder. February 1925-November 1941.
  - Porterfield, Sallie C.--Administrator of W. J. Elmore Estate, May 1924-October 1925.
  - Porterfield, J. E.
    Two notes and two contracts signed by Porterfield. Contracts concern the purchase of sheep and horses by Porterfield from MPF. September 1908-November 1916.
  - T. G. Porterfield
    Present are deeds, loans, and contracts executed by MPF for Porterfield. There is also a statement of accounts for the estate of G. T. Porterfield. August 1911-October 1937.
  - W. R. Powell Estate Papers, etc., March 1910-March 1918.
  - Road Matters
    Several drafts of petitions, bills, and resolutions presented to the Virginia Assembly concerning improvement, construction, and maintenance of public roads in Giles County. January 1920-c.1927.
  - J. S. Robertson Estate, June 1915-May 1922.
  - S. G. Ratcliff, February 1921-August 1923.
  - E. S. Ratcliff
    MPF attempted to aid E. S. Ratcliff in his efforts to obtain full insurance benefits from the U. S. Veterans Bureau owing from his son's death. Mrs. Landona E. Ratcliff was receiving monthly check as a beneficiary of her son. Upon her death, E. S. Ratcliff sought to transfer the benefits to himself acting as administrator of his wife's estate. November 1922.
  - Riggs, Louvenia S., June 1921-August 1923
  - Sinking Creek Valley Bank
    Incorporation papers for the bank are present as well as several collection cases handled by MPF. In one incident, it appears A. L. Farrier resigned as cashier when his books came up $450 short during an audit. In another, Martin Williams, MPF, and A. L. Farrier were investigated by a state commission to determine their relationship to three lumber companies who borrowed heavily from the bank before folding. July 1912-May 1931.
  - B. A. Smith, December 1925-August 1946.
  - Stebar Estate, January 1924.
  - Shumate, Victoria E., et al--Executors (2 files), March 1914-December 1927; March-June 1928.
  - Stafford, George F.--Guardian, April 1924-October 1925.
  - Scott, W. H., May-July 1921.
  - Snidow, W. B., May 1947.
  - MPF Taxes, April 1934-October 1945.
  - Trinkle, E. Lee, Governor
    Correspondence between Governor Trinkle and MPF concerning various bills before the General Assembly. The question of building a new system of public roads in Virginia seems to be a much-discussed issue. November 1921-December 1923.
  - Virginia--Carolina Joint Stock Land Bank
    MPF accepts a position as title examiner. Except for three letters between Farrier and company representatives, the majority of the material consists of blank forms. August 1922.
  - Virginian Supply Co., April 1915-July 1945.
  - Wills (copies)
    Copies of wills: K. R. and N. L. Shumate; J. L. Harris; A. S. and J. W. Miller; B. L. Hale; L. L. Teel; Nannie Gordon; J. M. and M. J. Tuggle; C. E. Sonner; M. C. Bolton; E. J. Draper; A. L. Caldwell; and E. A. Keister. June 1922-November 1945.
  - Woolwine, W. D., November 1926-November 1938.
  - Wilkinson, E. H., June 1926-July 1929.
  - White, Mamie and Lula
    Acting as guardian, MPF controlled a small amount of money belonging to each girl, from which he paid for items like schoolbooks, clothes, medicine, etc. until the girls came of age. May 1904-December 1919.
  - Williams, Eliza P., November 1918-February 1943.
  - W. C. Caudill v. Virginia Hardwood Lumber Co., March 1943-July 1944.
  - Bank of Giles County--Notes and Deeds, December 1939-June 1943.
  - Abstracts of Titles, March-October 1945.
  - Bank of Giles County--Notes and Titles, March 1935-June 1940.
  - Eads, Ernest, et al, June 1944-January 1945.
  - Church Matters
    Williams and Farrier and Farrier handle various matters for several churches in Giles County. Most common is the buying, selling, and granting of church land. November 1935-February 1943.
  - Craig-Giles Iron Company, May 1934.
- Box 3, 1894-1945 (Bulk, 1935-1945) (Box 3)
  Office files from Farrier and Farrier (abbreviated F&F), mostly from M. P. Farrier (abbreviated MPF).
  - Deeds and Titles (2 files), January 1942-December 1944; January-November 1945.
  - Corporation Commission
    Blank forms for incorporation of companies. undated.
  - Epling v. Epling, November 1943-February 1944.
  - Federal Land Bank of Baltimore, August 1934-December 1940.
  - Farmers and Merchants Bank-Rich Creek, December 1926-October 1942.
  - Gwinn, Lula H., May 1940-August 1942.
  - Hale, Virgie B., Estate, April-October 1945.
  - Hoge, Haven, September 1941-January 1942.
  - Horton, E. W. v. Ellen E. Taylor, et al, September 1935-May 1941.
  - Jefferson Standard Life Insurance Co.
    [empty file]
  - Kimbalton Lime Co., September 1922-January 1936.
  - Frazier Kidd--Tenant Purchase, August-December 1942.
  - King v. Overstreet et als, July 1944-December 1945.
  - Linkous, R. T. Estate, November 1940-January 1945.
  - Lindsey, Giles G. Estate (2 files), February 1939-October 1943; 1938-November 1939.
  - Miller, James Robert et al, October 1941.
  - Morris Plan Bank v. Johnston, September 1938-April 1943.
  - Narrows Water Co. Ins. v. Gearheart, T. H. and wife, February 1942-January 1944.
  - Pearisburg, First National Bank of, v. Ellen St. Clair Brown, et al
    Materials concern MPF's sale of Brown's interest in land to pay off debt to the First National Bank of Pearisburg and Sinking Valley Creek Bank. (See also Horton, E. W. v. Ellen E. Taylor, et al file.) August 1929-November 1942.
  - Province v. Johnston, February 1933-February 1939.
  - C. H. Price Estate Lands, March 1941.
  - H. L. Riner Estate, April-June 1943.
  - Stewart, C. H. v. Roy Lucas
  - Snidow, G. G., March-April 1942.
  - H. B. Sheldon Co., October 1941-May 1942.
  - Maggie Songer et al v. James Williams et al, August 1936-August 1937.
  - F. E. Snidow, Trustee v. Henry Gusler, et al
    MPF represented Snidow who sold land he held in trust to pay off the owner's (Lula Gusler) debts. The remaining funds were distributed to Henry Gusler and other heirs.
  - U.S. Fidelity and Guaranty Company and Sammons-Robertson Co. v. Luther Lafon and Co., May 1934-September 1935.
  - Wheelwright, William H., Jr.--Executor, January 1940-May 1943.
  - Williams, Mary Byrd, June 1938-July 1943.
  - Williams, Martin--Estate and Titles (4 files), May 1894-November 1941; June 1935-April 1938; April 1924-November 1941.
- Box 4, 1903-1934 (Bulk, 1920-1929) (Box 4)
  Files from the offices of Martin Williams and M. P. Farrier (abbreviated MPF). Subjects range from Appalachian Electric Power Co. to Norfolk & Western, in rough alphabetical order. 1903-1934; mostly 1920s.
  - Appalachian Electric Power Co.-Abstracts (2 files)
    Abstracts for land parcels in Giles County bought by Appalachian Electric Power Co. January 1924-May 1926; February-March 1929.
  - Bland County Lumber Co. (6 files)
    Scope and Contents note
    IRS requests for detailed statement of 1917-1918; income tax reports from the company, June 1921-January 1922. Income tax reports for 1921 and 1923, December 1920-December 1923. Notes concerning asses and liabilities of the company, December 1919-June 1924. Statements of shipments by the company, November 1919-December 1920. Claim against Strange Mining Co. seeking compensation for converting to war production and re-converting following World War I, November 1922. Materials concerning business operations, January 1920-January 1922.
  - Robert Blankenship v. Wilburn, November 1927-March 1928.
  - Mrs. Beatrice Abels Booth v. J. H. Booth, February-March 1928.
  - Nancy B. Blankenship v. G. P. Stovall, September 1923-February 1925.
  - Bland County Lumber Co. (2 files)
    Williams and Farrier correspondence as representation for the company, in particular land sales, timber and mineral rights, and contracts, January 1924-October 1927. IRS requests for tax reports, March 1922-June 1925.
  - Camp Manufacturing Co. v. C. A. Umbarger, July-October 1917.
  - Perry C. Cook v. Red "C" Oil Company, March-September 1928.
  - Commonwealth v. Charles Stump
    File suggests either MPF or Williams served as trial judge, October 1921-January 1922.
  - Mildred Charles v. Cyrrill Charles, January 1926-March 1929.
  - Mrs. W. D. Carter v. Burton Banks, February 1927-October 1929.
  - Mrs. Craig v. Pulaski Authority Co., October-December 1927.
  - Commercial Credit Company v. C. H. Johnson, September 1925-December 1926.
  - C. and P. Telephone Co. (legal transfer), January-November 1929.
  - Craig-Giles Iron Co. v. Commonwealth of Va. and Craig County, April-May 1927.
  - Golema French Dunford, et al. v. Essie French, April 1926-February 1929.
  - H. L. Dunn v. C. N. Williams, May-June 1925.
    File contains a deed between Dunn and J. H. Jervis, but makes no mention of Williams.
  - East River Lumber So. and St. Clair Receiver, February-November 1908.
  - Elmore v. Elmore (file empty)
  - William Elmore Estate Partition, October 1924-June 1925.
  - G. J. Elmore v. Buron Meredith, May 1927.
  - English-Ott Lumber Co. v. Shank Milling Co., March-December 1924.
  - Etowah Monument Co. v. G. O. Stafford, October 1927-March 1928.
  - English-Ott Lumber Co. v. Union Trust Co., December 1927-February 1930.
  - Federal Land Bank v. W. H. Fanning, et al., December 1927-January 1930.
  - Federal Land Bank v. Edward S. Eaton, et al., April 1928-August 1929.
  - Fidelity and Casualty Company of New York v. Day (notice), August 1928-April 1929.
  - Federal Land Bank v. Clarence H. Johnson, November 1926-June 1927.
  - Flat Top Grocery Co. v. J. E. Medley, c. June 1919.
  - Easley Freeman et al v. Ella Stafford, April-July 1927.
  - Posey Farewell vs. Farewell, c. June 1922.
  - Joe Farwell v. Mary Farwell, November 1926-January 1928.
  - J. W. Frazier and Son, September 1926-December 1927.
  - Federal Land Bank (4 files)
    Bland County matters, March-October 1926. Tazewell matters, April 1927-September 1929. Suit v. I. P. King, March 1927-June 1929. Foreclosure suits, land sales, farm loan applications, title abstracts, detailed loan applications, April 1917-November 1929.
  - Highway Commission v. J. W. Neal, July-October 1927.
  - Andrew and Thomas Huff v. J. J. and Minnie Blankenship, June 1926-November 1928.
  - O. F. and India Hendrickson v. D. Z. Sessler, September-November 1927.
  - Highway Commission v. C. E. Stables, April-August 1927.
  - Highway Commission v. W. M. Smith, November 1926-February 1928.
  - Mrs. Lula C. Hoge, Huntington, WV, property sale, January 1926.
  - Holland, Chas. G. (land sale), November 1926-February 1927.
  - H. W. Hale v. W. A. Johnston, undated.
  - J. E. Hopkins v. W. S. Brown, estate, May-July 1927.
  - Honacker, J. C. et al v. Highway Commission, July-September 1927.
  - Heatherington v. M. L. Johnston, October 1926-February 1928.
  - Highway Commission v. Fred Musselman, Janaury 1927.
  - Highway Commission v. C. A. Brown, April 1927-April 1930.
  - Highway Commission v. G. E. Fletcher, March 1927-August 1930.
  - Highway Commission v. Fetter Blankenship, July 1927-April 1930.
  - Kirk, Christian T., Estate, c. September 1922.
  - Lambert, A. A., et al v. C. W. Burton, c. July 1929.
  - C. W. Lucas v. Lucas, November 1927-March 1928.
  - Ann Lamb v. Giles W. Lamb, July 1927-May 1928.
  - Lucie Lafon v. S. E. Meredith, May-June 1927.
  - Ida Lucas v. Industrial Commission of Virginia, August 1920-June 1921.
  - Margie Leffel v. Leffel, June 1927.